Queer|Art|Film Collection MSS.327
Fales Library and Special Collections
Queer|Art|Film Collection
2010 - 2014
2010-2014
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sachs, Ira
Baran, Adam
MSS.327
3 boxes Videorecordings, posters, and flyers. One oversize flat box.
Queer|Art|Film is a monthly film series hosted by the Independent Film Channel (IFC) Center where queer artists exhibit and speak about their favorite films. The Queer|Art|Film Collection contains video documentation, posters, and flyers.
Historical Note
Queer|Art|Film, founded in June 2009, is an on-going monthly series hosted by the Independent Film Channel (IFC) Center in downtown New York City. Every month, a queer artist picks a film that has inspired them, and presents it to an audience. Afterwards, there is an informal discussion followed by a question and answer (Q&A) session with the audience. Co-curated by BUTT magazine editor Adam Baran and filmmaker Ira Sachs. For more information visit their website at: Queer|Art|Film.
Scope and Content
The Queer|Art|Film Collection is a mixed media collection of posters, flyers, and video recordings documenting one of the premier queer monthly film series in the United States.
The collection is divided into 3 series:
Series I: Advertisments: This series contains flyers and posters utilized to advertise the monthly events.
Series II: Video Recordings: This series contains video documentation of the presenters' introductions and audience question and answers (Q&A). Tapes do not include the feature film.
Subseries A: Videos: List of videotapes.
Series III: 2014 Accretion
Arrangement
Material is arranged chronologically by date.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ira Sachs in 2011.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Lesbianism in motion pictures.; Transvestites.; Film.; Independent filmmakers.; Transgender people.; Gay men.; AIDS (Disease); Homophobia.; Drag balls.; AIDS activists.; Gay activists.; Homosexuality and motion pictures.; Fosse, Bob, 1927-1987; Katz, Jonathan (Jonathan D.), 1958-; Musto, Michael, 1955-; Fassbinder, Rainer Werner, 1945-1982; P-Orridge, Genesis, 1950-; Lucas, Craig, 1951-; Coppola, Francis Ford, 1939-; Matmos (Musical Group); Deitch, Donna, 1945-; ACT UP (Organization)
- Series I: Advertisements
  - Queer|Art|Film Summer 2010-Fall 2011 Postcards (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Queer|Art|Film Summer 2010 Posters (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Queer|Art|Film Fall 2010 Posters (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Queer|Art|Film Summer 2011 Posters (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Queer|Art|Film Fall 2011 Posters (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Queer|Art|Film Spring/Summer 2012 Postcards (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Queer|Art|Film Winter 2012 Postcards (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Queer|Art|Film Winter 2012 Posters (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Queer|Art|Film Winter/ Spring/ Summer 2013 Postcards, Winter 2013 - Summer 2013 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Video recordings
  - Subseries A: Video recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
    - Genesis P-Orridge presents "If…," Introduction and Q&A, November 15, 2010; ID: 327.0001 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0001)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Original format: Mini DV
      Duration: unknown
      Scope and Content
      Featured: Adam Baran (Curator), Genesis P-Orridge (Presenter)
      Videographer: Conrad Ventur
      Program Content: Genesis P-Orridge introduces the film "If..." in which actor Malcolm McDowell stars in a social satire of fascistic British mores and boarding school torture. "If..." holds special meaning for presenter Genesis P-Orridge, the pandrogynous founder of industrial bands Throbbing Gristle and Psychic TV. Raised in the UK, Genesis underwent years of bullying at a British private school he/rself, noting that the film "is not nearly as vicious and appallingly sick psychologically as it really was for me."
      Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    - Pamela Sneed presents "One Sings the Other Doesn't," Introduction and Q&A (Part 1, 2, & 3), December 13, 2010; ID: 327.0002, 327.0003, 327.0004 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0002, 327.0003, 327.0004, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0004)
      Original format: DVD-R (three discs)
      Duration: 31 minutes
      Color, Sound
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Pamela Sneed (Presenter)
      Videographer: Ursula Mann
      Program Content: Poet and performance artist Pamela Sneed presents this rare screening of Agnes Varda's film "One Sings the Other Doesn't," a story about an intimate friendship between two very different women. Inspired by Varda's experiences traveling in the US and witnessing the birth of Women's Liberation at the end of the 1960s.
      Existence and Location of Copies
      DVD access copy available.
      Currently available. (Three parts on one disc.)
    - Michelle Tea presents "The Outsiders," Introduction and Q&A, January 31, 2011; ID: 327.0005 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0005, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0005)
      Original format: HDV
      Duration: 28 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Pamela Sneed (Presenter) Videographer: Ryan Colletti
      Program Content: Director Francis Ford Coppola's adaptation of S.E. Hinton's novel is presented by writer Michelle Tea, founder of the queer spoken word performance company, Sister Split. "The Outsiders" stars actors Patrick Swayze, Matt Dillon, Tom Cruise, C. Thomas Howell, Ralph Macchio, Emilio Estevez, Rob Lowe, and Diane Lane who become players in a violent gang war between rich and poor teens in the early '60s.
      Currently available.
    - Craig Lucas presents "Alice's Restaurant," Introduction and Q&A, February 28, 2011; ID: 327.0006 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0006, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0006)
      Duration: 32 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Craig Lucas (Presenter)
      Videographer: Ryan Colletti
      Program Content: Arthur Penn's film, "Alice's Restaurant" is based upon Arlo Guthrie's autobiographical song. For playwright/filmmaker/librettist Craig Lucas, the film "carried with it such an ineffable ach of sorrow...that it wiped the smirk of bohemia right off the face of the 60's." Guthrie plays himself in the film, reenacting his persecution at the hands of small-town local law officals, and in Penn's follow-up to "Bonnie and Clyde," Lucas saw, "the birth of a kind of American moviemaking" that he knew he wanted to be a part of.
    - Jonathan D. Katz presents "Pink Narcissus," Introduction and Q&A, March 21, 2011; ID: 327.0007 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0007, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0007)
      Duration: 39 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Jonathan D. Katz (Presenter), James Bidgood (Director, Pink Narcissus - Q&A Participant)
      Program Content: Jonathan D. Katz, curator of the censored 2010 LGBT National Portrait Gallery show Hide/Seek, screens director James Bidgood's "Pink Narcissus." Bidgood's film imagines a young hustler's journey from innocense to depravity, and has multiple cameos by playwright Charles Ludlam.
    - Su Friedrich presents "Desert Hearts," Introduction and Q&A, April 25, 2011; ID: 327.0008 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0008, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0008)
      Duration: 33 minutes
      Featured: Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curator), Su Friedrich (Presenter), (Liz Brown, Film Q&A Participant)
      Program Content: Filmmaker Su Friedrich presents director Donna Deitch's 1985 film "Desert Hearts," a movie that was as radical in the mainstream when it came out as Friedrich's own highly personal films have been within the avant-garde. As Friedrich puts it, "It took 'Desert Hearts' to introduce the mainstream to our world (or at least a corner of it set in Reno, Nevada, circa 1959) and more importantly to give us something to really enjoy while we ate our popcorn - large, please, with butter."
    - Emily Roysdon presents "Johanna D'arc Of Mongolia," Introduction and Q&A, May 23, 2011; ID: 327.0009 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0009, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0009)
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Emily Roysdon (Presenter) Videographer: Ryan Colletti
      Program content: German feminist filmmaker Ulrike Ottinger's film, "Johanna D'arc Of Mongolia," greatly influenced presenter, artist Emily Roysdon. She writes: "Ottinger's work re-imagines the impossible. Her characters, their lives and their environs, are beyond counterculture. They make new worlds." Ottinger's film stars French actress Delphine Seyrig, in her final screen role, as an ethnographer named Lady Windermere who befriends six other women on the Trans-Siberian Railway, then gets captured by a Mongolian warrior princess.
    - Dee Rees presents "Paris is Burning," Introduction and Q&A, June 27, 2011; ID: 327.0010 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0010, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0010)
      Duration: 38 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Dee Rees (Presenter)
      Program Content: Jennie Livingston's documentary "Paris is Burning" took America on a then-unseen journey into Harlem's vogue scene, following a cast of queens who serve maximum realness dealing with issues such as AIDS, poverty, racism, and homophobia. The film's portrayal of a marginalized community left its mark on filmmaker Dee Rees, who writes, "The themes of freedom, expression of identity, and finding family/community are universal."
    - Kate Bornstein presents "All that Jazz," Introduction and Q&A, July 15, 2011; ID: 327.0011 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0011, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0011)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Queer/Art/Film Curator), Kate Bornstein (Presenter)
      Program Contents: Director-choreographer Bob Fosse's "All That Jazz" is a favorite film of "sadomasochistic transsexual dyke and gender outlaw" Kate Bornstein, who first saw it upon its release in 1979. "All that Jazz," is a psuedo-autobiographical musical starring Roy Scheider as Fosse's alter-ego Joe Gideon. Gideon, a pill-popping womanizer, is struggling to choreograph his latest show and avoid the beautiful Angel of Death played by Jessica Lange.
    - 1. Jack Ferver presents "The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant," Introduction and Q&A, 2. Andrew Haigh presents "Saturday Night, Sunday Morning," Introduction and Q&A, August 22, 2011; September 26, 2011; ID: 327.0012 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0012, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0012)
      Duration: 57 minutes
      [1] The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Jack Ferver (Presenter)
      Program Contents: Choreographer Jack Ferverhe presents the film "The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant," which features Margit Carstensen as a lesbian fashion designer who manipulates her assistant, daughter, mother, and lover. Ferver calls the film a "wickedly funny, sexy, and gorgeous film about how insane we can all be."
      [2] Saturday Night, Sunday Morning
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Andrew Haigh (Presenter) Videographer: Ryan Colletti
      Program Contents: British filmmmaker Andrew Haigh presents Karel Reisz's film, "Saturday Night and Sunday Morning," which stars Albert Finney in his debut role as a rebellious factory worker juggling relationships with both a girlfriend and a married woman. The film's raw subject matter and style had a influence on Haigh, who writes: "Its exploration of the 'outsider' battling the mainstream is a theme essential to both the queer experience and to the kind of stories I want to tell."
    - robbinschilds presents "Desperately Seeking Susan," Introduction and Q&A, October 24, 2011; ID: 327.0013 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0013, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0013)
      Duration: 30 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Sonya Robbins and Layla Childs (Presenters)
      Program Content: The 1985 film "Desperately Seeking Susan" is a tale of two women whose personalities meld and shift - something guest presenters, choreography duo robbinschilds (Sonya Robbins and Layla Childs) explore in their dance-based video pieces.
    - Michael Musto presents "Pay It No Mind: Marsha P. Johnson," Introduction and Q&A, November 28, 2011; ID: 327.0014 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0014, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0014)
      Duration: 40 minutes
      Featured (Introduction): Adam Baran (Queer/Art/Film Curator), Michael Musto (Presenter) Featured (Q&A): Panel Discussion with Adam Baran, Michael Musto, Randy Wicker (Marsha's former companion), Agosto Machado, and Jimmy Camicia (Co-founder of the Hot Peaches Theatre Troupe)
      Program Content: Columnist Michael Musto, with Marsha P. Johnson's friends and companions, presents the world premiere of Michael Kasino and Richard Morrison's powerful documentary, "Pay It No Mind," which depicts the life of Marsha P. Johnson. Johnson was a revolutionary trans activist, Stonewall instigator, Andy Warhol model, drag queen, prostitute, and Saint, as well as a downtown NYC fixture from the 1960's through her death in 1992.
    - Matmos presents "The Servant," Introduction and Q&A, December 19, 2011; ID: 327.0015 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0015, Box Shared Fales 133, Dvd 327.0015)
      Duration: 41 minutes
      Featured: Adam Baran and Ira Sachs (Queer/Art/Film Curators), Drew Daniel and M.C. Schmidt, both of the band Matmos (Presenters)
      Program Contents: Joseph Losey's film, "The Servant" is a favorite of Drew Daniel and M.C. Schmidt of the musical group Matmos. Daniel writes, "the real center of this movie's power comes down to the slow burning, competitive, passionate bond between two men." "The Servant," adapted from a Harold Pinter screenplay, depicts aristocratic blonde Tony (James Fox) who hires butler Hugo Barrett (Dirk Bogarde) to look after his house, but soon the roles begin to shift.
    - Jack Pierson presents "Come on Back to the Five and Dime Jimmy Dean," Introduction and Q&A, January 30, 2012; ID: 327.0043 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0043)
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Jack Pierson (Presenter)
      Program Content: Photographer Jack Pierson fondly recalls the excitement amongst his friends (Mark Morrisroe & Tabboo!) over the arrival of Robert Altman's 1982 cult classic, "Come on Back to the Five and Dime Jimmy Dean, which starred Cher in her first breakthrough role, along with icons Karen Black, Sandy Dennis, and Kathy Bates.
    - Elizabeth Streb presents "Runaway Train," - Introduction and Q&A, February 27, 2012; ID: 327.0044 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0044)
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Elizabeth Streb (Presenter), Laura Flanders, Yve Laris Cohen
      Program Content: Choreographer Elizabeth Streb presents Andrei Konchalovsky's 1985 thriller "Runaway Train," which inspired Streb to start an Action Lab that would similarly stretch the boundaries of human possibility. For Streb, the film is also a very queer reminder that 'in choosing whom we love, we break all rules'"
    - Rose Troche presents "Postcards from America," - Introduction and Q&A, March 19, 2012; ID: 327.0045 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0045)
      Original format: DVD-R
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Adam Baran, Rose Troche (Presenter)
      Videographer: Xavier Marrades
      Program Content: Presented by filmmaker Rose Troche, who worked on "Postcards from America" while finishing her own queer groundbreaker, "go fish." According to Troche, "Postcards from America" "epitomized a moment when we began to believe in our voice...and represents the beginning of a community and collectivity that still exists.'" The film is a passionate, sad kaleidoscopic ride through New York gay life, the film highlights the intensely personal nature of Wojnarowicz's work, from his Jersey roots, to his years hustling on and off the West Village piers.
    - Moe Angelos presents "The Killing of Sister George," - introduction and Q&A, April 23, 2012; ID: 327.0046 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0046)
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Moe Angelos (Presenter), Jess Barbagallo
      Program Content: Originally planned to be presented by NYC drag legend Lady Bunny, the 1968 Robert Aldrich film "The Killing of Sister George" is presented by playwright/ performer Moe Angelos.
    - Laurie Weeks presents "THUNDERCRACK!," - Introduction and Q&A, May 21, 2012; ID: 327.0047 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0047)
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Laurie Weeks (Presenter), Angela Dufresne
      Program Content: Author Laurie Weeks (Zippermouth) presents the 1975 Curt McDowell film "THUNDERCRACK!" Weeks first saw the film in 2000 and says: "Guided by humor, curiosity, and sheer delight in the black-and-white gorgeousity of its own anarchy, the film is queer to the core."
    - Peter Cramer and Jack Waters presents "Salo, or the 120 Days of Sodom," - Introduction and Q&A, June 11, 2012; ID: 327.0048 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0048)
      Featured: Ira Sachs, Jack Waters (Presenter), Peter Cramer (Presenter)
      Program Content: Legendary East Village artist and activist duo Jack Waters and Peter Cramer present Pier Paolo Pasolini's 1975 masterwork "Salo."
    - Heather Matarazzo presents "I Could Go On Singing," - Introduction and Q&A, June 23, 2012; ID: 327.0049 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0049)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Heather Matarazzo (Introduction, Q&A)
      Videographer: Alex Diaconis
      Program Content: Actress Heather Matarazzo presents Judy Garland's last film "I Could Go On Singing." For Matarazzo, the film conveys "the experience I've had of feeling personally so uncomfortable in my own skin, continually asking others to validate who I am, and it truly never being enough."
    - George Chauncey and Ronald Gregg present "Rope," - Introduction and Q&A, August 20, 2012; ID: 327.0050 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0050)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), George Chauncey (Q&A), Ronald Gregg (Q&A)
      Program Content: George Chauncey, author of the seminal "Gay New York: Gender, Urban Culture and the Making of the Gay Male World," and noted queer film theorist Ronald Gregg present Alfred Hitchcock's 1948 thriller "Rope."
    - Larry Kramer presents "Jules and Jim," - Introduction and Q&A, September 24, 2012; ID: 327.0051 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0051)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Larry Kramer (Q&A)
      Videographer: Jess Byers
      Program Content: Playwright and activist Larry Kramer ("The Normal Heart," "The Destiny of Me") presents Francois Truffaut's 1962 film "Jules and Jim." According to Kramer "with 'Jules and Jim,' Truffaut broke almost every rule on how to make a movie how it looked, sounded, was acted, edited, photographed, scored, and especially for me, how it was scripted. Though not often discussed as a gay love story, it has one - not an especially bold one, but then the French can be rather joyously naive about certain things, and sex is one of them."
    - Flotilla DeBarge presents "Norman...Is That You?," - Introduction and Q&A #1, November 19, 2012; ID: 327.0052 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0052)
      Tape recorded without sound.
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Flotilla DeBarge (Introduction, Q&A)
      Program Content: Flotilla DeBarge presents George Schlatter's 1976 film "Norman...Is That You?" adapted from a Broadway play of the same name.
    - Flotilla DeBarge presents "Norman...Is That You?," - Introduction and Q&A #2, November 19, 2012; ID: 327.0053 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0053)
    - Erin Markey presents "Annie," - Introduction and Q&A, December 10, 2012; ID: 327.0054 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0054)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Erin Markey (Introduction, Q&A)
      Program Content: Singer, actress, and playwright Erin Markey presents John Huston's 1982 film "Annie." The story resonates with Markey, who says "I worked it out so that I could turn the age of 18, leave my parent's house and become a queer - AKA an orphan. Being queer in a world that generally considers it criminal or invisible means that there is not really a map for what a successful life should look like. Being an artist helps too. So Annie's movie musical orphan lifestyle seemed like the most exciting fit."
    - Tom Kalin presents "Three on a Match and Bubbles," - Introduction and Q&A, January 14, 2013; ID: 327.0055 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0055)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Tom Kalin (Introduction, Q&A)
      Program Content: New Queer Cinema pioneer Tom Kalin ("Swoon," "Savage Grace") presents Mervin Leroy's 1930 film "Three on a Match and Bubbles." Kalin says, "At an impressionable age, I stumbled upon the mirror-world of Pre-Code films on late night television...these movies dared to show marital discord with pleasure-seeking female protagonists who flouted convention."
    - Geo Wyeth presents "The Brother From Another Planet," - Introduction and Q&A, February 18, 2013; ID: 327.0056 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0056)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Geo Wyeth (Performance, Q&A)
      Program Content: Musician and performer Geo Wyeth, who released his first studio album "Alien Tapes," presents John Sayles's 1984 comedy "The Brother From Another Planet." The film's connection between "alienness" and "blackness" resonated strongly with Wyeth: "I wish I had seen this as a teenager...If you have ever felt your own body permeating unseen dimensions or worlds, unreachable by language or logical perception, you will connect to this film."
    - My Barbarian presents "Ashik Kerib," - Introduction and Q&A, March 18, 2013; ID: 327.0057 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0057)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Alex Segade and Malik Gaines of My Barbarian (Introduction, Q&A)
      Videographer: Jackie Zimmerman
      Program Content: The Los Angeles-based performance group My Barbarian presents "Ashik Kerib," the last completed film by Sergei Parajanov ("The Color of Pomegranates"). The director was influential on My Barbarian, in large part because of his "ability to imbue depictions of folk cultural forms with a queer sensibility and magical eroticism in the face of Soviet power."
    - Yoruba Richen presents "Set It Off," - Introduction and Q&A, April 15, 2013; ID: 327.0058 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0058)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Yoruba Richen (Introduction, Q&A)
      Program Content: Documentary filmmaker Yoruba Richen presents Gary Gray's 1996 film "Set It Off." According to Richen, "When 'Set It Off' came out we had a reason to go to the movies on a Friday night, bring our dates and swoon over butch Queen Latifah and beautiful Jada Pinkett. The film showed black women being bad and sexy and going for what we wanted. I ate it up and began to dream that maybe one day I could make films that showed us in all of our complexity - fearless, flawed and determined."
    - Viva Ruiz presents "Ms. 45," - Introduction and Q&A, May 6, 2013; ID: 327.0059 (Box 2, Media ID: 327.0059)
      Featured: Adam Baran (Introduction, Q&A), Ira Sachs (Introduction, Q&A), Viva Ruiz (Introduction, Q&A)